okay let's go back to the text
and we'll do about
45 minutes more right tim i think so
let's see
okay next part uh
i'm just going to read it for you for
good luck
solid
[Music]
he's talking about this
devas right which are very powerful
beings
they were very nice
in their last life they were very
generous
they did not study dharma they did not
understand emptiness
but
because they were so generous
then they were born as a very powerful
and very wealthy
being
then
he talks about
if they are coming from their own side
then they couldn't change and and this
is a very difficult idea
that we can talk about
and the question is after we die
and
or when we came into this world
why is it we cannot remember
uh where we came from
you know
and it's a big question
and
if we could remember
uh where we were before
if we could easily remember
our past life
then uh i think we would all be nice
people you know there would be no
international tensions either
uh if we could remember our past life
and
i think sometimes uh when we are
studying buddhism
we don't ask the obvious question
which is why we don't remember
past life you know if i had a puzzler
then why can't i remember it uh why why
is it completely
unknown to me
to me you know and i think if we are
honest
i think if we're honest many of us can
say
oh i have some feeling about where i was
in my past life
but if you're honest
i think you can say i i don't really
know
i don't remember
uh where i was sometimes i feel i have a
feeling
you know
like i have a feeling definitely i
wasn't a cook in my last life
because my cooking is so
bad uh
and like that but i don't really
remember uh
my past life and and why is that you see
why is that
and this whole poetry here
the whole story
is
you
if you expect that you could remember
then you don't understand where you're
coming from if you think
i should be able to remember my past
life
then you don't understand
where you are coming from okay you still
have a feeling
that there's a me
who had my past life body
and who had my past life mine
and
in the
there's a middleweight school
it says uh
they believe that michael
is my awareness of my thoughts the
person
listening to my thoughts
is michael
and and that feels right right it feels
correct
i
i'm listening
i i i have a body
but i'm not my finger gesture is not
guess last finger you know
gestala has gesla's finger that's why we
call it geshe-la's
finger
so there's a gestula
and he has those uh fingers so but he's
not the fingers
you know
so
gesla must be
kind of gets a lot of spirit
and then that spirit moves from
from life to life so there's geshe
michael
then
he dies in this life he gives up this
body
we can see it
what the body gets left behind guess
like goes somewhere else
and then we have to bury the body or
burn it or something
so we can we feel like
there must be a real gishla
who goes on
and and
he leaves this body
and he goes to another world you know
we don't know what happens to the mind
right the mind is invisible
you can see the evidence
of another person's mind
in their in their eyes in their how they
smile
how they frown
you can see evidence that they have a
mind
on their face
and what they do
and what they say but but you cannot see
the other person's mind
but we feel like well
if
if gesla left his body behind
probably he took his mind with him you
know his body is here
but
gesla
and
maybe like gesla
is mixed up with guest last mine
uh he probably went for another life to
another world
and he left this body
and then gesla will take another body
later and that's how we talk about it
and that's how we think about it you
know you
gesla exists
inside his body
then the body gets old
and gesla
gets out of that car and he moves to a
new car and he keeps driving you know
and
we feel like that and that's what the
first pension alarm is talking about
here
he's talking like when we change life we
feel like
changing cars or something you know you
get out of one car in your old car
and then you get in your new car and you
keep going you know
but what he says is
there is nobody getting out of the old
car
and there is nobody getting into the new
okay that's not you
that's not who you are
okay
you also leave your mind
behind
when you get out of the old car
uh you leave your body we can all see
that
but you also leave your mind okay and
you leave michael you leave your michael
okay it's not like there's some michael
and i know
buddhism talks like this but it's only
because of
language problem okay
it's not true
michael
gets out of his old body
and then goes to bardo
for seven weeks 49 days
and then gets into his new body it's not
like that that's not correct
if it's like that
some people should be able to remember
the old car right
okay
hang on i gotta go turn off the soup
again i'll be right back
my llama gave me a nickname
uh
50 30 years ago he called me burner the
burner of all the pots i burned all the
pots in the monastery
sorry i'm still doing it
it's not that geshen michael gets out of
his body
and goes someplace
listen this is what the
this poem is talking about
new seats open
new goshi michael opens you see i'm not
a guy
who changes cars from life to life it's
not like that
right now my seats are opening as gesla
and gesla's body engaged last month
then those seats finish
and geshla's body stops and gestures
mind also stops
and then new seeds open
okay
uh
10 minutes after i die
new seeds are open there's no gesla
who exists at that time
okay it's just more seeds
it's just more seeds opening and that's
a completely different
person
he of course he can't remember
what he was before okay of course he
cannot
he's completely
different seeds opening okay of course
he cannot remember
nobody
who can remember
it's just a new body
and it's a new mind okay it's it's not
gestalt got out of his whole body like
an old car
and get into a new body like a new car
it's not like that
geshe-la's
old car seats and gesh last old mine
seeds
and geshe last geshe-la's old scenes
finish
okay
now new seeds will open
and he will be a completely different
person
and of course he won't remember anything
because he's a different person
different mind
okay and i i know it's not how we
usually talk about it
but the purpose of this poem right here
is it's very interesting okay and and i
you know i like to tell my students
how long does it take
for
for geshe michael
to become a dog
you know how long does it take
uh
dude that's is it really true
uh geschlag goes to bardo
spirit realm
for seven weeks
and then if he's lucky he chooses a new
car and
no it's not true you see
the seats are opening
65 per second 65 per second
so
how long does it take
to get into a new car
and also get into a new mine
and get into a new person
it takes 1 65th of a second okay
so
i don't know why we feel safe
you know if i die
oh it's okay i i got seven weeks to
figure it out you know
people will pray for me
geshla will pray for me
and i it's not such an emergency you
know i have seven weeks
to
to choose good seeds for future it's not
like that okay
your states will open
in one sixty-fifth of a second it
doesn't take an hour
to become a dog it takes less than one
second
to become a dog you don't have to wait
for the dog's body to grow
okay it's not like that
okay
your whole mind
your whole body
can change to another
kind of being
in
in one second okay
you don't
don't think uh oh yeah i have seven
weeks to prepare you know don't worry
guys like
i have seven weeks to uh
find a good a good body good next buddy
it's not like that
what seeds you have when you die
they will decide what you become it's
not your choice
it's not even your choice to be you
okay
that's not even your choice what seeds
you have
in your mind when you die
uh
is what you will become and it's not
your choice you don't have any power
if you have good seats
that guy is going to be really nice
happy
and every bad seat you have there's
going to be something wrong with that
guy
okay
so
if you
if part of you came from his own son
then you could say oh geshe-la's going
to the bottle
let's do prayers he will listen to us
maybe he can remember his good seeds you
know it's not like that you're
you're gone
you leave your body
you leave the old car and you also leave
the old driver
and then you become a new car and a new
driver okay it's not like the driver
goes from one car to the other car okay
it's not like that
okay
now these guys who are
we're taking uh let's follow the text
for a while
otherwise there's a danger we won't
finish it in a hundred years
uh
he says look uh
those
beings super beings devas you know by
the way they are so powerful
you have to imagine
this is a possible future life
possibility
they are
you know there's this child's game
called marbles
you you play with little round
pieces of glass or
metal you know
uh marble game
kids game you know
those are devas
they play with planets like that okay
whole planets
it's not just iron men okay
they they when they have
fun
they can throw a planet they can throw
mars over the sun you know they can do
things like they are very powerful okay
but they also have this problem
they think uh the pen was made in japan
they they think they bought the pin
they're still thinking like that
okay they have wonderful seeds are
opening
they have the power to play with planets
like throw planets like baseball
but still they don't understand why
uh they don't understand
it's all seeds opening from their past
life okay
uh
and then how can they start to feel
attachment for anything okay how can
anything
start
you know how how do things start
and we can talk a long time
about why something good starts in your
life
or why something bad starts in your life
but to put it briefly
you cannot point to the moment
that this pen became a pin okay you can
say
oh gesture the pen was made in japan
when
november 3rd
it came out of the factory
yes but what was the exact time
when it became a pin
and you cannot find that moment you see
you cannot find the moment
that this pen
became a pen
when did they finish making the penguins
oh it was nine o'clock
and 30 minutes
and 10 seconds
that's when it came out of the factory
yes but is that when the front part came
out of the factory or when the back part
came out of the factory you know guess
what it doesn't matter
about
10 minutes after nine
it came out of the factory yeah but
actually
this is very difficult idea
[Music]
it must be one side of the pen came out
of the factory first
you know maybe there's a conveyor belt
and this this came out of the factory
and then the end came out of the factory
there should be some time difference
oh this
this part of the pen came out of the
factory uh 10 minutes after nine
and
14 milliseconds
and then this part of the pen came out
of the factory
ten minutes after nine at 15
milliseconds
but when did the middle come out of the
factory okay
does it really matter
it must be 14 and a half milliseconds
okay
yeah but what about the front end of the
half and the second the back end of the
house gesla
who cares
listen
you cannot tell me the time
that the pen came out of the factory
because there are pieces of time
in the
at that time which are too short for you
to see okay
try to understand one second
one second has a beginning and an end
okay
one second in time this much time
it has
beginning of the time
and it has the end of the time
and it lasts for some time okay time
start
time end
okay
but there should be some smaller pieces
of time here right
but your mind cannot see those smaller
pieces of time okay i i don't want to
see let's see
i'm planning to bake a cake today
for my wife i
they say it's not healthy i don't care
when you're sick
and someone makes you a cake you feel
happy right
so
that uh cake uh it will have many parts
right there will be the top part
there will be the middle part
there will be the bottom part now listen
if the parts of the parts are too small
for you to see
if you cannot see the atoms of the cake
then you cannot see any part of the cake
okay
if you cannot see
the pieces of the cake
then you cannot see the cake gessela
i know i can't see adam of cake i know
that
but when you put many atoms of cake
together you can see that
no you don't understand
when you put many atoms of cake together
and you say oh look i can see now now i
can see it's not too small now i can see
but still there must be atom here
and still there must be atom here
and using the edge of the atoms
if you cannot see the edge of the atoms
you cannot see the cake the point is
cake is not made of atoms cake is coming
from you
okay
time is not
coming at you time is coming from you
rebirth
in another body and another mind is not
coming at you
it's coming from you it cannot come at
you
that the atoms in this pen
cannot come this way
you can't see them
you they're too small you cannot see
them
if something's too small to see
and you put a lot of them together
you wouldn't be able to see the edge
anyway
because the edge would be one atom okay
here this would be the edge of the atom
if you can see the edge of the pen
it proves the pen is coming for you and
not from the pen okay it's very
interesting
okay
if you are hoping
that you had a pretty good life
and you did pretty good things
and after you die
you'll get a pretty good new car
uh
that's a wrong idea there's no cars
and there's no drivers
it's just
more things coming from your seats
things are coming out of your seats
there's nobody watching
what comes out of your seeds
you are coming out of your seeds okay
you are not watching
what's coming out of your seeds
you are
what's coming out of the water also
coming out of the scene okay
don't think uh you own your body
you own your house
you have your job
they're all coming out of seats okay
nobody owns your job nobody owns your
body
no one gets a new car
it's very
interesting and all the things
in your life
all the colors
all the sounds
all the shapes
they are coming from your seeds
and the person seeing them is also
coming from your seeds and there's
nobody else
there's nobody who had the seeds okay
it's not like that
okay
all right let's go to the next verse
then there's a
story
that this devas
they have
beautiful children
okay
they're called
it means the
daughters and sons of the gods all right
and
uh
when the
devas people in temporary heaven when
they look at their uh
daughters or their kids
they feel this intense attachment to
them okay
and they don't realize
that the kids are coming from their own
seats you see uh oh guess
somebody had a baby oh
veronica and my friend she had twins uh
last week
and
also my
my her son's goat had two two babies
last week we had two human twins
and we had two goats
uh
in the same week right
and then the lady was so happy and she
sent us a photo it's very beautiful the
two boys are
each one is drinking from one breast
she's got two two small boys and
she's feeding them at the same time
and
she was so happy you know
when you have a child
and it it feels to you
like the child came out of your
womb
and you feel very proud and you feel you
feel
a deep contentment fulfillment
oh i gave life to another being you know
uh
and and you feel a strong attraction to
that being
but actually he says here
uh
you're not seeing your children
correctly okay you don't understand
where those children come from
they are coming from your seeds okay
those children were born from your seeds
and
you created you
and you created your pregnancy
and then you created the
the children who came out of you
and it's all your seeds okay
if you understand where your children
really come from
then
then when you see them you would want to
be nice to everybody you see if you
understood
who really created your children
it's the good seeds in your mind
and then uh
sometimes when we have a family
i don't know why but some people
uh
after they have children
they become more compassionate i i saw
it many times in my life
people who are
selfish
uh become more
compassionate after they have children
and they they learn how to sacrifice
their own happiness for another person
when i was in the diamond business
i you know i had to hire hundreds of
people
i had to hire them i had to interview
them and i have to find them
interview them
hire them
train them
for for 19 years
hundreds and hundreds of people
and after a few years i i realized
uh moms are great workers you know moms
are number one
workers if you want a good worker
uh
choose a mom
you know they know how to sacrifice they
know how to stay up late
they know how to finish the job
you know the father will go to sleep if
the baby cries but the mother will never
go to sleep you know
and uh
so i i always used to hire uh
i used to look for moms uh because they
they know how to sacrifice so
sometimes
when you when you see
a person who has a child
it makes them even more compassionate
you know
and then sometimes
uh
in my in my observation i never had a
child but
when you have a child your
clay claeshas your mental afflictions
get more
you get more attachment
uh
you get more anger uh you
you get more selfish you you take care
of your kids
but you don't take care of other
people's kids you you have a deep
prejudice
i should take care of my kid
but i i don't have to take care of my
neighbor's kid you know not equally
you know so
what they're talking about here is
misunderstanding
where did your children come from
and they're using deva children they're
talking about david children hey
you know how devas have children
they don't have uh the tradition says
the children pop up in their lap
they don't come out of their body
just sudden one day boop there's a kid
in their lap you know
and it seems like a very easy way to
have a baby right
so the idea is here
uh
when children uh come out of you
there's two ways they can go number one
you can understand
that this beautiful precious thing
is coming from the seeds
of sharing things with other people and
then after you have your child
you take even more care of other
people's children like that
or
if you don't understand where the child
came from
then the birth of the child can be a
disaster you become more
you you become more
you protect your child and you don't
really care so much about other people's
kids
you know so either way it can go if you
understand
your child was born from seeds
then you then you will understand
that
that you should take care of everyone's
children equally okay
all right
uh
now
there's an interesting uh
dynamic
with the devas
and
their whole life
is wrapped up with
competition
okay and it's very similar to
wealthy
human people okay
uh
i i heard a
i listened to the radio
late at night when i come home from work
it's a beautiful drive it takes me about
45 minutes
i live in the country i don't live in
the
i live on a mountain
and even i have a dirt road
and uh when i drive home at night
it's a it's a very beautiful drive and
and sometimes i will listen to the radio
and
i'll hear things from other
other places you know
like other states i i will hear the
radio
uh
from
from completely different places okay
and
then i
i hear these famous people the actors
movie yesterday i heard an interview
and they even uh talk about the other
actors in the movies
and they say my competition
competition
you know and that's how they are
thinking these beautiful people very
handsome very good looking ladies and
men you know very very
famous
i don't know why they don't have kobe
tummy like me
they always look
exactly
very beautiful you know
but the more beautiful you are
physically
and the more famous you get
then the habit is to get jealous or
competition
with other beautiful people it's a curse
it's a very bad problem
of successful people wealthy people
beautiful people
they feel
sometimes they can feel intense
competition for each other
or intense jealousy
of each other and uh
they now they're talking about that now
the punching llama says
you know
these people have a beautiful life these
devils
and then
but the one thing that defines their
life
the the most important part of their
is jealousy
you know it's not enough to be number
one actor
it's not enough to win the
movie award you know
they are
constantly
checking out each other
oh she's more beautiful she's more young
or he's more strong
he has more
fans more people are following him
than me
and this is uh
talking about
uh
the emotions
of this devas
they have two big emotions
number one
when they have a kid
they feel this intense love
for their kid
okay
and then
when they see another demo
they get this intense jealousy
and this intense feeling of competition
so
punching llamas
saying
look let's think about those devas
let's think about those
very beautiful people
rich beautiful people
two things define their life number one
they have their
own children
and intense attachment to those children
and
beautiful love for their children
but then at the same time
they feel intense jealousy
for the other famous people or the other
beautiful people it's
strange that these very successful
beings
should have uh intense
attachment
and intense love for their children
and at the same time they feel this
intense jealousy
for other successful people and
pension llama is not saying
oh you should be a good person
you should love other people
the way you love your children he's not
saying that
he's not saying that it's very
interesting what he's saying
okay don't forget
this is a fight between the devil and
the angel okay
this is a fight
between the devil and the angel the
devil says
oh look geshe michael
inside your mind
two different kinds of thoughts
number one
big compassion and love for your
students
that's so nice okay
then number two
intense jealousy
of other teachers for example okay
oh
he's not saying that
he's not saying that first pension llama
is not saying that
he's not saying
look
you have good thoughts
and you have bad thoughts
and please try to have more good
thoughts
and please try not to have bad thoughts
he's not saying that
he's saying nobody is having those
thoughts
he's saying
nobody is having those thoughts
nobody has the love for their kin
and nobody feels the jealousy for their
competition nobody is there
to have the feelings
that's devil talking
if the dharma teacher tell you
please try to increase increase your
loving thoughts
and please try to
decrease your competition thoughts
if the dharma teacher tell you like that
they don't know what they're talking
about
because
when i tell you you should have more
good thoughts like you have for your
children
or you should not have competition
thoughts like you do for your
other people at work
when i tell you that i'm talking about
you but there's no you you see
there's no you if you think there's a
you
who has the loving thoughts to your kids
and if you think there's a you
who has the competition thoughts at work
then already you lost the war
you already lost the war i'll say it
again
if you think there's a you
who's having the loving thoughts
and if you think there's a you
[Music]
who's having the competition thoughts
and if you think you should have more
loving thoughts
and that that you should have less
competition thoughts
you already lost the war
you're already listening to the devil
because there is no you
there is no nobody's having those
thoughts
gestala
why are we having this class okay
if there's no me
to improve myself
and if there's no me
uh
who will get worse if i don't study
then why are we having this class if
there's no me there is no you
there's just seeds
there's just seats okay there is no you
nobody got out of the old car
and get into the new car
nobody loved their own children
and hate the other people's success
there's no you
it's just
seeds opening
it's just seeds opening
well gesh left there's no mean
how can i be happy
who becomes a buddha
nobody becomes buddha
that buddhist is open
then you're buddha
got it
so don't worry about me
i'm hearing somebody's open mic by the
way it sounds like you're chewing on
tinfoil
uh okay
there's no me
uh having happy thoughts there's no me
having unhappy thoughts you are your
happy thoughts
and you are your seeds opening okay so
don't worry about me
just worry about the seeds okay
when you see yourself being
loving to your children
you are watching your own loving seats
open
when you see yourself being competitive
to uh other
other people
you are just watching competition seats
open okay
that's all
so
what am i supposed to do guest love
well try to understand
you are watching seeds open
and you have to focus on the seeds don't
focus on me
don't focus on me
just focus on seeds okay
yes i have trouble meditating yeah i
know
it's a seeds opening
yo watching seeds open
okay last thing
then we'll take questions okay tim
uh
i told this story a couple times but i i
don't know grandpa teaches so many days
of the year i forgot what story i told
i have a problem this is my kitchen okay
you guys can see my kitchen
uh
and uh
basically
when i wake up at night and i sneak into
the kitchen to sneak some
snack that my wife doesn't hear
i keep stepping in the water you know
there's always water on the floor
and
uh every night quietly
i will step in the water barefoot it's
very cold it's winter here also sunum we
don't have snow but
then it's cold the water is cold
then i i feel responsible
i i feel like i'm a good person i
i should clean up the water on the floor
and i will get down on my hands and
knees
and i clean up the water i said oh maybe
the dishwasher made some water or i
don't know
maybe we spilled some water
and actually i cleaned up the water on
the floor for
five or six nights
uh like
every night i get down on the floor and
i clean the water
and then suddenly
i don't know what happened
i said i'm tired of cleaning the water
maybe there's a
a pipe leaking
you know maybe i should fix the pipe
you know
like it's
it's so much work to clean up the water
every night
maybe i should find out where it came
from
okay so that's what we're learning here
uh don't
focus on
the result
focused on the seats and i called my
friend daniel garcia
and
he came and
he got under the sink and he fixed the
pipe he fixed the leak okay
so what the first pension llama is
saying here
is uh
just worry about your seeds take care of
your seeds
don't focus so much on the result okay
just take care of your seeds
also
when you feel intense love for your kids
and you feel intense jealousy at work
that's also coming from faith okay so
take care of those things okay don't
worry about me
don't think about geshe michael get him
michael jason michael
the love
is coming out of seats
and the jealousy
and the geshe michael
jealous is coming out of seeds
and the geshe michael loving
is coming out of seeds so work on your
seeds work under the sink
find the pipe
fix the pipe okay
the pipe is your seeds the problem is
the person working on the seeds
is also coming from the seeds
the person who's working on the seeds
is also coming from the seeds therefore
whatever seeds you have more
also make you
better seed worker or worse seed worker
seeds
make more seeds
and there's nobody in control
okay what seeds you have now
probably you will be similar tomorrow
okay
because they are creating the person
who's working on the seeds okay
the seeds are creating the same person
who's trying to fix this thing
and if there's a problem with disease
then there's a problem with the scene
fixture also
okay
it sounds like sansara you know it
sounds like a vicious circle
it sounds what you said it sounds like
we cannot improve ourselves
it's difficult
but it's not impossible as long as you
understand
things are coming from seeds you have
hope
and if you forget that then you don't
have hope okay keep focusing on the
seeds keep focusing on the season okay
if you have bad seeds
it's because you come from bad seas
then guess what how can i fix myself
how can i fix my bad scene
if i'm coming from bessie's
it seems like it's impossible
no because you can do small things we
are lucky
that seeds grow we are lucky
that seeds grow
double double double double double
double you can do a small nice thing
today
if you can do one small nice thing
then there's hope
because those seeds double double double
double okay
so today
practical step
if you want to have a good
rebirth okay
then just do some small good things okay
that's all
just do some small good things
i'm making a soup okay it's not very
good soup
uh
you know i'm not a very good cook
i'm my tibetan is better than my soup
but do small nice things for other
people
and dedicate those new seeds okay and
let's all dedicate them to uh
international
tension
solutions okay let's all do some
small
good thing today like make a soup
i'll let you guys know how it comes out
tomorrow okay if i burn it or not
but uh
do some small good thing
dedicate the seed the seed will explode
the seed will expand
okay make small good seeds
and let them grow
that's our only hope
all right timothy you got questions from
me i think we got
another
i don't know 20 minutes or so something
like that
yeah
okay
stop that
okay cool
all right kesha thank you for teaching
us today
my pleasure thank you for asking
so
this is this uh this question continues
on with the you had said about focusing
on the seeds and not focusing on me
and a couple questions have come in
about
when we're when we're talking about
seeds through the various schools like
in the mine only school the seeds are
stored in
the kunchi right in in the near the
heart
and then you go to the upper middle way
and
we kind of say things like the seeds are
stored in me or in the you know what
comes out of the seeds so the questions
are wondering like can you explain this
a little bit to us so we can we can hold
on to how do we why do we get taught
that it's in it's stored in us
but then you're saying to us now that
you know don't focus on me focus on the
seeds themselves that seem like outside
of me
okay good question good question
uh
look in the lower schools
buddha says be a nice person you know
try to make good seeds
and then when you die
you will
get a a new body and a nice body
and you'll be in a good place okay so
you know that's
that's
first turning up the wheel that's how
buddha talks to beginners
please please make good seeds
you're gonna die
you want to have a a good rebirth you
know so please make good seeds
then you can carry them like a suitcase
to your next life
and you can open them there you know
what what the first pension llama
is trying to say here
is
don't forget
that the person
who's working with the seeds
is also coming from seeds at the same
moment
okay so
the person who's trying to improve their
seeds
the person who who is making the new
good seeds
in that moment they are also coming from
seeds you see
the seed maker
is also coming from
so if you understand that
you have a chance
but if you think there's a seed maker
who is not coming from seeds at the same
moment
you're gonna have trouble okay you're
gonna have trouble
okay so try to understand
the seed maker
is also coming from seeds for example
if the seed maker is in a good mood
today
then the seed maker will make some good
seeds okay
and if the seed maker is in a bad mood
today
then the seed maker won't make any seeds
today you see so you have to
understand
that the seed maker
is also coming from seeds and and we
need to
plant the seeds
that will make us a good seed maker
okay the seed maker
the seed planter
is also coming from seeds
so
we have to pay attention
to planting the right seeds
to be a good seed maker
okay
so
we have to spend some time
to think about
why am i
happy
to plant seeds why do i understand seeds
why do i believe in seeds
there are special seeds
to believe in seeds
and that's the root of all seeds you see
so
what first pension lamb is saying
is
take care of the seed maker think about
it okay why are you in a mood
to come to this class today you planted
seeds before
be careful with those seeds take care of
those seeds okay don't lose those things
which means
keep encouraging other people okay every
time you see somebody do something good
tell them you know wow that's so cool
what you're doing you know this whole
thing about rejoicing
a coffee meditation aimed at other
people
uh that's the real
seeds
to make you a good scene maker okay so
take care of your seed maker seeds
okay what's the best way
uh
just tell other people how cool our day
you know
and and do it all the time
by the way don't lie
don't make a
story oh you're so nice if the person is
an
don't tell them they're a nice person
that's not going to help them okay
i'm not saying that okay
i'm saying when you see something really
good
that somebody else is doing
then tell them how cool is that and and
it's kind of selfish
if you don't tell other people
how cool what they are doing
wow i saw how you talked to that
difficult person today you are so cool
i saw how much patience you had
you know i just want to say it's
beautiful it's i wish i could be patient
like that you know
and that's all
those encouragement seeds
to other people
makes you a better seed planter it's
very cool
so uh watching other people
telling them how cool is their seed
planning
honestly when they are when they are
cool
uh
then that makes us a better seed planter
that's all the first pension mama's
talking about okay
where we plant the scenes
uh i think it's i think the mind only
school is useful
uh word just finished his uh first book
word smith
uh he just finished his first book on
the mind only school i think it's the
greatest book
about the mind only school ever
translated i i think i think it's the
best book i ever saw
about the mind only school and it's it's
ow it's a
diamond cutter press okay look him up
online
diamond cutter press the book is called
the golden key
and if you really want to understand uh
mind only school
then get that book and chew on it and
ask word smith ask askwordsmith
ask wordsmith to teach some classes
about it okay
and it's amazing i
i read a sentence recently
that just
blew my mind
and it's by zomkapa who's always correct
and he said look
if you really understand
the mind only idea
about the refrigerator where you keep
your seats if you really understand it
then you can practice
then tantra is successful then then you
can practice the secret teachings you
can live with the angels
uh if you really understand that
so i was like whoa
that's pretty cool you know
so i really encourage you to uh
to to study that book
then many people told me gesla
i bought the ebook
by the way it's instant
gratification it's so cool
with the ebook
uh you just order it and you get it in
30 seconds okay
so you don't have any excuse about it
you know you don't have to wait for the
post office
it's lucky in america if you wait for
the post office
it might take two years to get the book
uh
so
you can get the e-book in about
less than one minute
you know
and uh
many people told me
oh get out of mind only school is too
difficult you know well there's two
things you can do okay number one
if a book is not difficult
it means you already understand it then
in my opinion there's no reason to buy
the book
okay if a book's easy for you
then it's because you already understand
those things
then in my opinion you you shouldn't buy
the book there's no reason to buy the
book okay
if you already understand something
then why should you buy the book you
know
uh in my opinion and some compass
tradition
we should buy the book which we don't
understand okay
uh
we should
we should get the book which we don't
understand
because then we can go deeper
and
and those mixed nuts man they worked for
five six years now
and each one
understand uh their own book uh very
beautifully i wanna show you something
let me see tim can i do
let me see if i can find it
sure
you can share the screen store
okay here i go
this is uh we're gonna show this this
week in the my in the mix nuts
classes okay can you guys see this
uh
and and uh you can you can read this
this week you can come to the mixed nuts
classes
these are the mixed nuts topics okay
i'm giving you a secret preview don't
tell me
okay
but here's where it all came from these
are the original sutras
two and a half thousand years ago okay
we are translating six of them
okay
then
uh let me get this
here's avid armor
okay
that's about 2 000 years
ago then comes the mahayana books
18 centuries ago
then comes the mind only school
asanga
1700 years ago
then comes
dharma kirti
and all the logic schools how to sing
okay
that's uh
1500 years ago
then comes the great morality schools
vinaya
that's 1300 years ago
then comes to tang dynasty in china
great great translators who brought the
wisdom from india
like yonsei and shenzhen
then comes the lower middle way
this is kamala
sheila great great writers like that and
they also loved
meditation
and they wrote the great books about
meditation this is 1300 years ago okay
they wrote the great meditation books
after that came higher middle way
this is chanda kirti
uh they really understand emptiness
amazing amazing guys
this is about 1300 years ago
how to develop the good part good heart
and that came a thousand years ago
then came in lamrim
the glory days about six hundred years
ago tongkapa
then came
the study of the different schools
in two different ways
studying all the great schools together
okay so there's them
those are the great ideas of the last
two and a half thousand years
now i'll show you something cool you
guys ready cinema i can see you're so
interested
uh
i'm gonna shrink this
okay
and here's the books okay that we're
translating on the side
okay these are we are translating six
sutras
okay three of them are translated
already they're already available you
can buy them
okay
all the kinds of karma
sutra of lapis light
commentary to the diamond cutter sutra
commentary to the heart center you can
buy all those they're finished
every
great subject
of ancient times is being covered by the
mixed nuts
on this left right sides you can see the
books of the mixed nuts
and they cover every great topic
every great topic
in the last 2000 years
is being translated by the mixed nuts
okay the mixed nuts books are on the
side okay
and there are 27 translations
and if you don't get them you must be
crazy
real mixed up no you're nuts
okay so anyway if you have time this
this week
uh we will have 60 classes
about this idea you asked me okay it's
not my fault tim you asked me about my
normally school
uh
if you really want to understand uh how
your seeds stay in your mind
come to the mixed nuts classes there are
27 different books
that we are translating that cover the
whole thing
all right tim let's do one more question
so this is a combination question
gestula from a few people
okay
they've asked about one person asked
about
that their their partner
has seemed to run out of love for the
family and and wants to leave
and someone else has asked about
themselves they seem to have run out of
compassion for other people they're not
able to
you know really
feel that for other people so what are
some of the advices you have you know
there's two different situations but
they're kind of similar seeing people
run out of love and compassion for
others
yeah i like the question
it's one of the saddest things in in the
world
on the one hand
you're in a relationship
and it seems like the other person is
losing interest
or it seems like they don't love you as
much as they used to love you
and it's very disturbing
it feels like water running through your
hands
and
it feels very
it's you you can feel it happening you
can see it's happening
and it it's a very very sad
you have feelings
this person had feelings
and now it seems like the the feelings
are going away on the other hand
uh sometimes i'm the person who's losing
the feelings
you know and
i used to care a lot about these people
my family or my partner
or my job
and now i i don't feel that passion
anymore uh i don't feel this uh
i don't feel love for them i feel
instead of
instead of love i feel obligation oh no
i i should be nice to them
this is my family you know this is my
partner
uh this is the company that hired me for
many years i
i don't have passion from them
i don't feel this passion anymore
but i feel
like i owe them something you know and
then
both are very bad feelings
oh i owe love
to my family but i don't feel it
and it's uncomfortable
or uh
look someone in my family or someone in
my company they
they don't seem to
have as much passion about us
or or or me
as they used to have and and both
feelings are the same thing right tim
you said that
it feels the same
love is being
lost or love has gone away
then uh what can we do about it and
and again uh
luckily
the first law of karma says
that small seeds expand
quickly
okay so
the first law of karma says
that sits double
every 24 hours if you understand scenes
okay so that's cool
it's like super fertilizer
okay
if you understand seeds
then the good seeds you plant
will grow
like crazy okay like crazy
so if you see love is being lost
uh
it's like water on the floor don't try
to fix the water on the floor
fix the pipe
fix the place where the water is coming
from okay
so
personally uh
and i i've had a long life so i've seen
uh love lost many times
uh it doesn't work i think
to uh go to the person and say look you
you don't look like you have much so
much love anymore
can you please improve yourself you know
you have a family you have a partner
you know we care about you please try to
have more in love
and i can tell you it doesn't work okay
because why it's coming from you
how much love they have
is coming from you
so you just have to plant
more seeds for love you know and that
can be appreciation
okay so think about the people
who are
serving you okay somebody's growing uh
the oranges for my orange juice
somebody uh planted their coffee beans
for my coffee
i saw how watermelon somebody planted
watermelon even in the winter
and
so many people taking care of me you
know i
i should show some love
even just gratitude
for the people i'm i'm living in in the
winter
in arizona it's really cold outside i'm
in the mountains
but somebody's uh sending me uh
electricity you know thank you you know
i i don't know where you are but i'm
i know if i pay my bill you send me
electricity and i'm warm
on a cold day and and just try
to show gratitude
for all the beautiful things in your
life and then
that plants the scene
that this love won't disappear the love
will come back okay the love is a big
big thing
the love of a partner
the love of your family
uh your own love for your family
other people's love for you
you can replant them
you can start that spark again
uh by showing gratitude for other people
okay oh thank you for
heating my house thank you for coffee
beans
uh
you know thank you for internet thank
you tim for organizing these classes
and working like a maniac all day all
night
to give us
all these chances you know show other
people gratitude
and the love will come back and it's
very exciting when it comes back when it
works
because because it's coming from seeds
right
it's very very nice
to know how to bring the love back in
your own heart
or from other people in your family it's
so cool
to be able to turn up the love
just just from your own side
it's like fixing the pipes right so
more gratitude seeds more gratitude
seeds more gratitude
okay
all right tim
see you tomorrow
yeah
and thank you again tim thank you really
for organizing all this and thank you
all the translators
i know tim has a huge
group of people supporting him and
and thank you so much i i know it's a
huge group of volunteers and thank you
very much and your translators
it's a headache to do this kind of
translation i know
and i don't know how you do it but god
bless you okay
all right